welcome to meditating with john vervicky
we do this every weekday morning at 9
30 a.m with mondays alternating between
a new lesson on today today is a dharma
day hence the whiteboard
and then a review of the whole ecology
of practices that we call
the quiet day if you're joining us for
the first time uh you're very welcome
um i strongly suggest you go to the
links in the description this video
and do lesson one right away you can
continue meeting with us
and do one or two lessons every week and
then you'll catch up with us
there's about almost i think close to
100 classes
that's all about meditating and
contemplating and qigong
and meditative movement
mindfulness-based
movement practices so those are all from
the eastern tradition we are now going
to shift over to the western
wisdom tradition to create a more
diverse and i think a richer and
powerful
uh ecology and practice reservoir
please like this stream to increase the
total visibility in the youtube
algorithm i'm trying to help as many
people as i can
there's in some sense the fact that
we're now into this more
ongoing endurance aspect of the crisis
is has its own difficult
and also difficult kinds of challenges
for people so please help me to help as
many people as possible
mondays wednesdays and fridays as we
start making our way through this
wonderful book of the wisdom of hypatia
we will be going a little bit longer on
monday wednesdays and fridays
generally uh unfortunately uh this
material is a little bit
more uh like a little bit more lecture
style as needed
in order to convey some of the material
give you guys some of the back
background that's needed at the end of
every session
there will be a question and answer here
please look at the questions at that
time
do anything from the entire ecology of
practices not just from the wisdom of my
facia but anything that
has preceded him if you have more
general questions
and i suspect that as we get into the
wisdom of medication more philosophical
more general questions
might occur to you uh please come to the
general livestream q a
on youtube at 3pm eastern time
the third friday of every month it will
be august 21st of
this month okay so let's get started
so how we will do this
is when when we're going through the
dharma aspects is i will do
uh like i said a bit of a lesson um
then we will sit and then we will do uh
as always we'll still do the chanting
we'll do
still do this etc
so we're doing the western tradition and
the pivotal figure
for that tradition is socrates
so just as the buddha was the touchstone
as we were going through the eastern
ecology of practices tradition
socrates would be to touch them all of
the groups that we're going to take a
look at
in the wisdom of hypatia the
the epicureans and the neil platonus are
deeply
influenced by socrates and they use
socrates as an exemplar
there's of course just like the buddha
just like jesus of nazareth
there are many different interpretations
of societies i'm not going to try and
offer you a single interpretation
because that's not
that's the point of what we're doing
here this is not a history class
what we're trying to do here is to
figure out the
best interpretation of socrates
relative to the individual movement
that was in response to him and those
movements were
what wouldn't zero on about zeroing up
on them is how
they generated ecologies and practices
for the cultivation of wisdom okay so
socrates is a pivotal figure it's
athenian philosopher
there if you go to episode 4 of
awakening from the meaning crisis
there is an extended discussion of
socrates there
first we want to take a look at is
somebody who was influenced by him which
is
who is epicurus now right away we have
to pause here because
the term that has come into our language
uh describing someone who follows an
epicurus
is epicurean the problem with that is
we it has gone through significant
decadence
so that most people when they hear
curious they hear
hedonism they hear the pursuit of
pleasure
largely through self-indulgence and
largely around
associated with food
now while epicurus has a lot to say
about pleasure
he is not advocating that kind of
decadent hedonism that's not what
epicurus is about at all
so i need all of us to put aside
the standard meaning of epicurean of
today
and we need to retrieve the ancient
meaning because our job here is to try
to retrieve the ancient ecology of
practices
okay so epicurus as i said everybody
takes
socrates as the touchstone and what
really
impressed uh epicurus about socrates
was socrates capacity for what
and this is a phrase that that the
curious is going to make famous
anoraxia anorexia
now that term is hard to translate
adoraxia is
often translated as tranquility that's
what the clinton does
sometimes it's translated as equanimity
so this is
this in greek this is the opposite the
negating
so like a theist is someone who doesn't
believe in god
so this negates what this basically
means is it needs
turmoil or tumult and so this means
a lack of turmoil a lack of tumult
and so you know now what epicurus is
actually on about
we have this phrase and it's it's also
not
as rich as it needs to be but we talk
about peace of mind
that freedom from inner turmoil inner
conflict
you know what it's like when we're
suffering
now epicurus is famous in fact for
saying call no man a philosopher who has
not alleviated
the suffering of others this was the
central concern
of his philosophy it wasn't about
indulgence
it was about the alleviation of
suffering now
the suffering caused by a lack of
anorexia the suffering caused by
inner turmoil inner tumors
let's remember that suffering primarily
means
a loss of agency
you are no longer the author of your
experience and its meaning
things have overtaken you that's why we
often use
another metaphor for when we're in
turmoil we talk about being
upset we're upset because now we've lost
control we've lost being centered we've
lost being balanced
and this is related to an important
model
disease we get our word disease from
this which is a lack of
ease which is not quite the same as
being easy
the things being easy so ease is more
like
a a fluency of flow
with reality all right
so epicurus
was really interested about trying to
he saw himself almost like the physician
of
the psyche he's very much the model of
being a doctor
almost like a psychotherapist today
and so what epicurus was interested in
is
well what's the disease and what's the
cure
and now you can see how we're right
getting into an ecology of practices
so for epicurus the
the reason why we are diseased the
reason why
we are in inner turmoil we're upset
is because we have
right we're uneducated
about our relationship to pleasure
and pain we're socialized
by our culture but that's not the same
thing as what
epicurus is talking about what epicurus
is talking about
is that we often are deeply
confused about pleasure and pain
so one way of putting it that is not
inaccurate
is epicurus wants us to bring a lot more
mindfulness
and reflective discernment to our
relationship
to pleasure and pain see epicurus isn't
about maximizing pleasure
epicurus is about trying as much as
possible
as much as possible to get you into
right relationship
with pain and closure
okay
so why are we confused well epicurus was
actually
deeply influenced by the atomic model
that was a model that was at the time
that all the reality was made up of
adam's emotion
it's going to be the basis of scientific
theory he was very scientifically
oriented
so it's completely appropriate that we
use the best science of today
to try and supplement to try and
supplement
that purist so what do we know
well we know that the way we pay
attention to
our and right the way we get pleasure
and pain of things
is affected by how salient
something is to us how much it stands
out to us because when things stand up
to us
they arouse us
okay so here's a basic feature that we
need to understand
about how things
arouse us so let's say this
is time
so this is the present and this is the
future and this is how
intense
how salient something is to us
and all organisms show this graph this
is called hyperbolic discounting
very rapidly as something that we're
thinking about becomes more in the
future
it loses its salience to us this is why
we procrastinate
because a present
pleasure can override
right so here's a pleasant pleasure it's
not very important
but because it's in the present it gets
magnified
here's a very future pain
but because it's in the future it gets
minimized so one of the things we have
to do
is we have to learn to widen our frame
we're going to talk about that not today
we'll talk about that later in the week
we can learn to widen our frame
this is a mindfulness exercise it's like
a contemplative practice
because we need to do stuff to
counteract this
on a regular basis
okay so we tend to therefore do what
we tend to confuse intensity with
importance we tend to confuse
intensity with importance and one way
you can think about what epicurus is
trying to get us to do
is he's trying to get us to invert that
he's trying to get us to
to train ourselves so that we find the
important
most intense you see that's a that's a
powerful inversion normally we confuse
how intense something is with how
important it is
but what if you could train yourself to
make the importance
more intense that's sort of the key
one of the key moves that we're trying
to achieve here
with epicurus okay
so
in the wisdom of hypatia mclennan is
recommending
a couple of basic practices that you
take up right from the beginning
right and one is self-examination so
socrates
remember the pivotal figure socrates
famously said the unexamined life is not
worth living
how much do we examine the processes
and the patterns of our pleasures and
pace how much
self-examination do we engage
mclennan also recommends a process that
i i like to call he doesn't call it this
i call that maximization
this is the collection of maxims
important
very pithy phrases that help to
very readily bring to mind principles
now here's where i can explain something
to you why are you doing
maxims because max the goal of maxims
are to open that frame up widen the
frame
so that you're not locked into the
present moment
if this is a little bit different
attitude towards the present moment
you're not locked into that hyperbolic
discounting
you're frame widening so you can get an
ability to discern between intensity and
importance
and so what the maxims do is they
maximize your afraid
they remind you important principles
that
open up your frame so i just gave you
one
the unexamined life is not worth living
socrates was going to die for that now
this means that
if we don't engage in a regular and
reliable practice of self-examination
our lives lose most of their values
fairly strong playing very strong
playing
so like all these maxims you have to
sort of take them with a little bit of
reflection
you don't absolutize them but there's an
important insight there
so we have to engage in the
self-examination
of pleasures and pains
okay so how do we do that okay so here's
the principle
maybe this is a maximum for you a maxim
for you
what we're engaging in is prioritization
for the ease of sustainability
prioritization for the easiest for the
ease of sustainability
prioritization for the ease of
sustainability
so what you're gonna do is right you're
gonna
when a desire comes up so we're gonna
talk
mostly today about desire because that's
about pleasure
and then we also are going to talk about
fear
uh because that has to do with pain but
this is for later
today we're concentrating on this one
okay so when you have a desire
and of course you're gonna also you'll
have an associated sense of
pleasure what you're gonna do back
what you're gonna do first is don't
immediately
look through the desire and now you're
going to see something that links up
nicely with
what we learned from buddhism step back
and look at the desire
don't look at the world through your
desire
automatically step back and look at the
and then something very analogous to the
labeling
categorize your desire categorize your
desire
so there's basically four stages you go
through you ask yourself
is is a desire natural or unnatural
this is the epicurean model what this
natural means it means that you can
honestly say to yourself
you need it right in order to heat
alive but there's right three lives you
lead
use your physical life so what do you
need to remain physically alive
is your mental life what do you need to
keep your mind
healthy and vital and your social life
what you need what you because you are
an inherently social cultural being
what you need to keep that alive and
healthy
so is this desire natural
you want a drink of water that's a
natural desire
okay is it necessary
so there are natural desires they
satisfy something
that has to do with our physiological
life our mental life or our social life
but they can be unnecessary so whereas i
need a drink
that's necessary when i'm thirsty i may
desire a bottle of pepsi
pepsi is unnecessary even though it's
satisfying a natural desire
so first of all you give priority
to desires that are both natural and
necessary
over ones that are natural and
unnecessary
see we're prioritizing next
next we consider desires that are both
unnatural and unnecessary
and then what is very so what's an
example of according to epicurus of the
desire that's unnatural and unnecessary
fame because we desire fame but this is
something i reflect a lot
on given my current context what i'm
doing
right it's it's you
many people live lives without fame so
fame is clearly
not natural and it's not necessary
now you say but i need status social
recognition that's a different thing
about the pursuit of faith celebrity
status that's both unnatural
and unnecessary so
you step back you look at the desire
you categorize the desire is it natural
is it necessary then you ask yourself
short term long term
can i satisfy this desire only short
term
or will i be able to satisfy it long
term and what you then
take a look at is you engage in that you
bring the principles in the maxims
they widen your frame and you say will
the satisfaction of this desire
will it will it satisfy these principles
so if i keep satisfying this desire will
it actually for example
reduce my capacity to examine myself
well then while i'm getting short-term
pleasure i'm going to be buying
long-term
pain
so that's how the maximization comes in
frame widen
to see oh right right
now then ask yourself another question
is it a mental pleasure or a physical
pleasure
and the argument of epicurus contrary to
what popular media is
is that mental pleasures are much more
important than physical pleasures
why because physical pleasures
are ones that are not unique to us as
human persons
mental pleasures of course are the
pleasures that
can if properly educated lead us
to wisdom lead us to virtue and epicurus
was very concerned
with the cardinal virtues with wisdom
and justice and socialism
and courage especially we'll talk about
that
okay so is it natural
is it necessary short term long term
maximization
now final fourth important question to
ask yourself
how easily can i obtain it
how easily can i clean it
because if it's very hard to obtain
then i'm putting myself at great at risk
of not
obtaining that pleasure and of falling
prey
to pain and frustration
now you don't start with how easy it is
to obtain you notice that
you don't start you'll answer all the
other questions first and then you ask
yourself
how easy is it to obtain because when i
answer all these questions correctly
what i'm getting is i'm trying to teach
myself to prioritize
those desires that seek the pleasures
that are most easily sustainable
what does that get me to well that gets
me to
one of the most important ways of
understanding
adoraxia we when we hear this
we hear this as a lack of
tumult a lack of turmoil and that's of
course right
but
it's right technically but it's wrong in
its connotation because
we should be hearing this as a positive
term
not as a negative term because what
i would argue epicurus was on about was
learning to to savor
the pleasure of being
the pure pleasure of being
being alive again the three lives
being physically alive mentally alive
and socially a lot we're going to see
how those all come together
when we talk about philosophical
companionships
friendship was the most important virtue
the most important practice for epicurus
so how do we get to the place
where we can savor
savor
almost
that positive pleasure they get so
backgrounded as we
layer and complexify our lives
so there's a practice and this is a
really important book
on this kind of work right
savoring a new model of positive
experience
i want to teach you savoring and what
we're going to do when we sit
is we'll chant we'll sit for a bit
a shorter meditation set and then i'll
also talk you through
the savoring practice okay this is also
something you should be doing
i recommend as if you're in a garden so
mcclellan talks about right
uh the epicureans are in the garden um
the
he uses pork for the soda that's wrong
it's one of the colonnade
the colonnade right and then the grove
doing the the savoring practice while
you're walking through
a natural environment is really optimal
but i'll show you how to do it even when
we're sitting
okay
so i want you to think of your
experience as having two features to it
perception this is in
in cognitive psychology music called
bottom up
and what you this is how information is
coming into you
what you want to do for savoring is you
want to first set you want to get in
that sense where you're opening yourself
up
trying to become more receptive more
sensitive you guys know how to do this
already because of finding your flow
finding your root okay this word
is a little less familiar prehending
this is
so pretending um it's like comprehending
grasping with your hand apprehending
this comes notion was from whitehead
this is basically your ability
right to grasp patterns to see
relations and so that's
considered coming top down and
the proceeding this bottom up so what
you're doing when you're walking
first of all you're trying to not have
any sentences or scenes in your mind
so it might be good to do you know a few
breaths of mindfulness
the past note when i'm walking
what i'm doing is i'm taking an attitude
i'm trying to put aside
all of these other complex patterns i
have a pursuit
of pursuing things and trying to come
into
a more fully engaged
perception of trying to open up and make
myself more sensitive
and so i'm noticing more differences and
more
colors and more shapes right and at the
same time
right it's not just passive though i'm
also
trying to do more pretending i'm trying
to almost like a little bit
like you know a detective i i'm trying
to pick up on
all i'm just trying to let my mind find
all kinds of patterns
some of those patterns will be
synesthetic it'll be almost like
i'm tasting colors some of them will be
you know like synchronicities i'll get a
sense of an
outer and inner meaning corresponding to
each other
some of it will be symptomatic i'll
suddenly get a sense of theme
the way to think about this this is
from this excellent book by john russon
is
it's almost like he talks about the
musicality of how we're making sense at
all times and we just
we forget we forget that but when i'm
when i'm moving around
it's like it's all almost like i'm
listening to music because
all of right all the noises
all of the textures all the colors are
coming in but it's not but my mind is
also sifting them and weaving
it it's making up music and what i get
out of that
is i get a sense of deep participation
because when when you're thinking about
music as the analogy and that's also the
analogy used
as i mentioned in taoism when i'm
hearing music
the rhythms are both outside and within
i'm feeling the rhythms within
in correspondence in resonance with the
with the rhythms without
i'm getting that it's it's almost like
i'm
it's a moving music of my mind and my
body
and so i participated and it's just in
the presence
of everything that's the way of
understanding being
remember that being is ultimately a verb
being is presence
and to refine that pleasure and presence
here
and it's so it and it's so invigorating
it's it's
you can feel how it it it enlivens the
body
and enlivens the mind and it already is
starting to set you
it's something to be in relationship
that will enliven you social
social sociability in your social life
i will review all of this on wednesday
and we will also go through some more
stuff
on wednesday because we've only talked
about one part of this i've
alluded to the fact that this is
something we also need to do in groups
uh we have to understand what
philosophical friendship
is and this was the the key thing
because
that's where we find most of the courage
we need
in order to deal with fear now i want to
point something out
i'm not going to teach every single
thing that's what i'm asking you to read
i want that to be more socratic my job
is to try
and amplify it and make it more
practicable to you
and integrate it with what you've
already learned i'm counting on all of
you to ask
questions that you might have from the
mclaren book and i will answer them
readily and reliable okay
so i think that's it for that let's get
ready to sit
we're gonna have a short set for 10
minutes
and then we'll talk about we'll do a
little bit of that presenting and then
we'll take some questions
one more time a gentle reminder that
um we we will be going longer on monday
wednesdays and fridays i just have to
get one thing here
all right so let's all sit
we'll begin together when i say begin
get yourself comfortable please put your
phones on do not disturb
we will chant you'll have a shorter
chance
shorter set and then i'll quickly go
over
just just for maybe a couple minutes
just that initial so get a sense
of what savoring is like you can also
savor and this is how it got confused i
think with
epic like what you mean by epic hearing
you can save her when you're eating food
you can savor anything and that's the
point
that's the point
all right
let's begin
[Music]
one
oh
[Music]
begin your silences
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character of communication
perhaps by reciting the five precepts to
yourself
as you start to come out of doing the
five promises
in a very receptive state
just look around your room have to have
any thoughts
sentences in your head any scenes
open yourself up you know this
you did listening and rooting but now do
it on your environment
the body of the world rather than just
your own body
use soft vigilance
move let your gaze move around
excuse me open up to more
as you're opening up
but you might apprehend more find
patterns
connections associations
almost like there's music
emanating from the room but also
the rhythms are within
opening yourself up to more
but you're also making more connections
opening yourself up more
making more connections you know this
this is finding your flow
soft vigilance finding your flow but do
it outside let it resonate within
get that sense of participation in
presence
to savor what it's like to just be here
just be here depth of it
you'll notice that it's similar in some
ways to alexio davina
and let that let those two talk to each
other in your practice
the lectio divina will also give you
will often give you maximums
will generate maximums from your lexus
all these things are now talking to each
other more
in your ecology practices now the best
thing to do is to savor
while you're walking in a more natural
environment if possible like in a garden
like epicurus and also saber while
you're eating food
you drink some liquid
when you touch something
it's obviously a moment of mindfulness
but it's also a remembering
it's a remembering of the deepest
kind of pleasure that is the most
sustainable pleasure
that's the pleasure that most allows you
to recover your sense of
agency and being in the world
no other pleasure does that like the
pleasure of
being okay so we're going to have
time for one question i'll take more
questions tomorrow a lot more
and also on wednesday we'll do a review
more questions
thursday like i said open this up
share questions from your practice from
the wisdom of hypatia but also comments
observation connections you're making
all the pre-hending you're doing
okay so i think we have one question
one second jason's just making some
adjustments
ah so here's a question directly related
to today's practice from kira
how do you not bullshit yourself on what
is necessary
so this is where i mentioned something
that
um that is crucial which is uh the
connection to science
so what you have to do is i mean for
your body you have to learn
what are the things that are actually
necessary for your body
and for your mind what are the things
that are actually needed
to have a healthy sense of mind
so a couple things that are helpful is
right you know you can we develop a lot
of attention to our culture to a healthy
body and
and we sometimes confuse that with a
body of a certain image so
i won't i won't say too much about that
and i'm going to hold offs talking about
the social life uh because we're going
to get that when we talk about
philosophical companionship so kiera
i'm going to concentrate on just the
mental life
so this is what i propose to you and
that this is not
directly epicurus but i think it's
consonant with it and i think it's a way
of extended epigenesis
what is the food of the mind
what is it we're actually generating
when we're doing the savory
it is meaning not just but i don't mean
just conceptual meaning that's primarily
not what we're doing we're doing the
meaning that is the meaning
what people talk about in meaning in
life that sense that's enhanced in the
flow state
that's enhanced in mystical experience
that's that sense of being
connected to the world to yourself
and to each other rightly what is needed
in order to afford to protect produce
and promote
those connections to oneself to
other people and to the world so such
that you feel
that you matter that you're connected in
a way
that makes a difference that i would
pose to you is the food of the mind
that is the health of the mind meaning
in life so
what is needed for making
meaning and the thing is this is where
we get most confused
this is where we confuse right intensity
with the importance but remember what
importance means import
you actually take in what nourishes you
when you ask people reliably
at different stages of their life what
makes your life
meaningful to you it is not the things
that are often occupying us with
intensity
because what actually makes people feel
like their lives are meaningful
are those experiences in which they
savor
the connectedness the connectedness to
themselves
to each other and to the world what is
needed for that that's the food that's
the
importance for the mind that should not
be confused
with mere intensity so like i said we're
going to do much more
this week please prepare yourself
regularly the mondays wednesdays and
fridays for the next while
are going to be longer because that's
just the nature of what we're doing
right we're following socrates here and
he's a more talky guy than the buddha
and so we got it we got to do that
okay but it still has great value for us
i want to thank you all for joining
i want to thank my beloved son jason
who's running everything today
and he's doing i think a masterful job
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video
also follow me on twitter about for any
updates about this stream
please invite others who might benefit
by joining this series
please get connected to the discord
server i'm going to try and talk to
mark and brett today i owe them an email
setting up a time
where we can uh get a space set up so we
can practice philosophical
companionships
the friendship that's so crucial to good
epicurean practice
reminder that we're doing this every
weekday morning at 9 30
eastern time remember
that continuity of practice
connectedness
is more important than sheer quantity
than sheer intensity
don't hold yourself to a standard of
perfection hold yourself to a standard
of virtuous friendship
and we're going to learn a lot about
virtuous friendship from epicurus
for there is no friend
greater to you than your own mind and
body
take care everyone i'll see you all
tomorrow
keep practicing bye
foreign